Do I look real to you?
هل أبدو حقيقية في نظركم؟
Hope so.
أرجو ذلك.
I have no idea if you're seeing this,
ليس لدي أي فكرة اذ كنتم تشاهدون هذا،
but I'm just going to look ahead and trust that you're there.
ولككني سأواصل وأثق أنكم موجودون.
I've drawn a semicircle in the sand in front of me
قمت برسم نصف دائرة أمامي في الرمال
so I don't walk past it and look like I'm floating in midair.
لن أقوم بتجاوزها وأبدو وكأنني عائمة في الجو.
Right now I'm standing
أقف الان
in the open air,
في الهواء الطلق،
on a beach under a palm tree,
على الشاطئ تحت شجرة النخيل،
in the exact spot where your stage used to be.
في نفس الموقع الذي اعتاد المسرح أن يكون فيه.
I have 12 minutes with you.
سأقضي معكم 12 دقيقة.
I set a limit.
وضعت حدّا أقصى.
My wife Navid once said
قالت زوجتي نافيد مرّة
that infinite possibility is a creator's worst enemy.
أن الاحتمالات اللامتناهية هي صانعة أسوء الأعداء.
For example, this dress: I'd asked her to design something
مثلا، هذا الفستان: طلبت منها تصميم شيء
that a priest might have worn in 23rd-century Cairo.
يكون أجمل ما ارتداه كاهن في القرن 23 في مصر.
But we only had three days to make it,
ولكن كان لدينا ثلاثة أيام فقط لصنعه،
and the only fabric we had
والنسيج الوحيد الذي نملكه
was an old duvet cover that another resident left behind.
كان غطاء لحاف قديم تركته أحد المقيمين وراءها.
But she did it, and it's perfect.
ولكنها نجحت في تنفيذ ذلك، وكان مثاليا.
And she looked at it and said,
ولكنها نظرت إليه وقالت،
"Proof of concept -- creation needs constraint."
"دليل على الفكرة-- الابتكار يحتاج قيودا."
So with these 12 minutes,
لذلك في 12 دقيقة القادمة،
I'm going to tell you about my greatest discovery.
سأخبركم بأعظم اكتشفاتي.
For my whole life, my obsession has been eternal life,
طوال حياتي، كان هاجسي الحياة الأبديّة،
as I know it is so many of yours.
كما أعلم أنه هاجس الكثيير منكم.
You may be happy to know that your research will pay off.
قد تسعدون لمعرفة أن بحوثكم ستؤتي ثمارها.
I am 318 years old.
عمري 318 سنة.
The average human lifespan is now 432 years,
يبلغ الآن متوسط عمر الإنسان 432 سنة،
and my work has been to extend the human lifespan indefinitely.
وتمحورعملي حول تمديد عمر الإنسان إلى أجل غير مسمى.
And I've never questioned that someday,
لم يسبق لي أن شكّكت في ذلك يوما ما،
we'll reach a point where we'll be content.
سنصل إلى مرحلة سنكون فيه راضين.
But the opposite keeps happening:
ولكن يحدث العكس:
the longer we live, the longer we want to live,
كلما عشنا أطولا، كلّما أردنا أن نعيش أكثر.
the less we want to die.
ونصبح أقل رغبة في مواجهة الموت.
Who can blame us?
من يمكنه إلقاء اللوم علينا؟
The universe is so big.
يتّسم الكون بكونه غاية في الضخامة.
There won't ever not be more to see.
لن يكون هناك أبدا المزيد لرؤيته.
Just yesterday,
بالأمس فقط،
I was reading about how you can take out a boat on Europa
كنت أقرأ عن الكيفية الي يمكن بها ركوب قارب على أوروبا
and sail from island to island all over the planet,
والإبحار من جزيرة إلى أخرى في جميع أنحاء الكوكب،
and some of the islands have villages that you can stay and visit
وتوجد في بعض الجزر القرى يمكنك البقاء فيها وزيارتها
and sleep under the shadow of Jupiter.
والنوم فيها تحت ظل كوكب المشتري.
And then there's this other island where there's just one songwriter
ثم يوجد هذه الجزيرة أخرى حيث يوجد فقط كاتب أغاني
who sits and plays mandolin for the ocean.
الذي يجلس ويلعب المندولين للمحيط.
And then there are others where there's no one
ثم هناك آخرون حيث لا يوجد أحد
and there never has been,
ولم يوجد فيها أحد أبدا،
and so you go just for the pleasure of touching your foot to sand
وتذهب فقط للتمتع بإحسال لمس رجليك لرمال
that no foot has ever touched before.
لم تطأها قدم من قبل أبدا.
You could spend 400 years doing just that.
يمكنك قضاء 400 سنة تقوم بذلك.
Right now the Moon is rising in the Northeast.
يظهر القمر الآن في الشمال الشرقي للبلاد.
I can see the cities on it with my naked eye.
يمكنني رؤية المدن بالعين المجردة.
They're connected like nerve clusters:
مرتبطون مثل تجمّع:
Mariapolis on the South Pole, and Ramachandran on the Equator.
ماريابوليس في القطب الجنوبي، وراماشاندران على خط الاستواء.
And New Tehran in the Sea of Tranquility.
وطهران الجديدة في بحر الهدوء.
That's where Navid and I met.
إنه المكان الذي التقيت فيه بنافيد.
We were both artists downtown.
كنا فنانتين من وسط المدينة.
The day we met, we were passing each other in Azadi Square,
يوم التقينا، مررنا بجانب بعضنا البعض في ساحة آزادي،
and we bumped shoulders.
واصطدم كتفان.
And I turned to apologize
التفت للاعتذار
and she, without saying hello or introducing herself or anything,
وبدون القاء التحية أو تقديم نفسها أو أي شيء،
said, "Well, why do you think we didn't just pass through each other?"
قالت، "حسنا، لماذا برأيك لم نمر فقط بجانب بعضنا ؟"
And first of all, I thought, "Who the hell are you?"
وأولا، تبادر إلى ذهني، "من أنتِ؟"
But second, the question annoyed me,
ولكن ثانيا، أزعجني السؤال،
because the answer is so simple.
لأن الجواب بسيط جدا.
I said, "We didn't pass through each other
أجبت، "لم نمر بجانب بعضنا البعض
because elementary particles have mass
لأن الجسيمات الأولية لها كتلة
and because the space between elementary particles
ولأن الفضاء بين الجسيمات الأولية
is filled with the binding energy that also has the properties of mass,
مليء بطاقة الارتباط التي تملك أيضا خصائص الكتلة،
and we've known that for 800 years."
ونعلم هذا منذ 800 سنة."
She must have been in one of those moods
كانت في واحدة من حالاتها المزاجيّة
where she likes to mess with strangers.
حيث يحلو لها العبث مع الغرباء.
Or maybe she was just flirting with me,
أو ربما كانت تغازلني،
because she looked at me and said, "I thought you'd say that.
لأنها نظرت إليّ وقالت، "تبادر إلي إنك ستفكرين هكذا،
Think deeper."
فكري بطريقة أعمق."
And then she took off her belt,
وخلعت حزامها،
this belt that I'm wearing now,
هذا الحزام الذي أرتديه الآن،
and she said,
وقالت لي،
"Our universe is built so that particles have mass.
"بُني عالمنا لكي يكون للجسيمات كتلة.
Without that basic constraint,
بدون القيود الأساسية،
we'd have just passed right through each other at the speed of light
قد نمربجانب بعضنا البعض بسرعة الضوء
and never even known."
وقد لا نعلم أي شيء."
And that's how our romance began.
بهذه الطريقة بدأت علاقتنا الغراميّة.
Navid and I
عند حديثي مع نافيد
never ran out of things to talk about.
لا تنتهي المواضيع.
Never.
أبدا.
It was incredible.
كان الأمر لا يصدق.
It was like we were both heroes climbing up into a mountain range together
كنا نشبه بطلتين تتسلقان معا مجموعة من الجبال
and we kept arriving at new vistas,
ونعمل للوصول إلى آفاق جديدة،
and these new, perfect constellations of words
وهذا أمر جديد، كامل، مجموعة من الكلمات
would come out of us to describe them.
ستصدر منا لوصف الأمر.
And we'd forget them as soon as we made them,
وكنا ننساهم ما إن نقوم بصنعهم،
and throw them over our shoulder and go on to the next thing, on and up.
ونتخلص منهم وراء ظهورنا، وننتقل إلى الأمر الموالي، وهكذا.
Or one time, Navid said that our talk was like we were always making bread,
أو ذات مرّة، وأخبرتني نافيد أن حديثنا كان مثل إعداد الخبز،
and that we were always adding in a little more flour
وأننا كنا دائما نضيف المزيد من الدقيق بكمية صغيرة،
and a little more water,
والمزيد من الماء،
and folding it in and turning it over
ونقوم بعجنه وتدويره،
and never getting around to baking it.
ولم نقم بطهيه أبدا.
If my obsession was eternal life, Navid's obsession was touch.
إذا كان هاجسي الحياة الأبدية، كان هاجس نافيد اللمس.
She had a genius for it.
كانت عبقريّة في ذلك.
All of her work revolved around it.
كان كل عملها يتمحور حول ذلك.
My body was like a canvas for her,
كان جسدي مثل لوحة زيتية بالنسبة لها،
and she would draw her fingertip down over my face so slowly
وتقوم بتمرير طرف اصبعها إلى أسفل وجهي ببطء شديد
that I couldn't feel it moving.
ل يمكنني الاحساس به يتحرّك.
And she was obsessed with the exact moment
كان ينتابها الهوس في نفس اللحظة
when I would stop being able to tell the difference between her body and mine.
عندما لا أكون قادرة على معرفة الفرق بين جسدها وجسدي.
Or she would just lie across me and dig her shoulder into mine
أو تكذب علي فقط وتدفع بكتفها نحو كتفي
and say, "Pilar, why does this feel so good?"
وتقول "بيلار، لماذا يبدو هذا جيدا جدا؟ "
I'd say, "I don't know!"
أُجيبها، "ليس لدي أدنى فكرة!"
And she always had a facetious answer for her facetious question,
وكان لديها دائما إجابة طريفق لأسلتها الطريفة،
but the answer I remember today is,
ولكن الجواب الذي أتذكره اليوم،
"It feels good
"يبدو الأمر رائعا،
because the universe chose its constraints,
لأن العالم اختار قيوده،
and we are its art."
ونحن قطعه الفنيّة."
It's always funny what you think the future is going to be like
من الممتع دائما ما كنت تعتقد أنه سيكون عليه المستقبل
versus what it turns out to be.
مقابل ما يحول إليه الأمر.
In your time, scientists thought humans could freeze themselves
في وقتك، ويعتقد العلماء أن البشريمكنهم تجميد أنفسهم
and wake up in the future.
والاستيقاظ في المستقبل.
And they did -- but then they died.
وقاموا بذلك، ولكنهم ماتوا بعد ذلك.
In your time, scientists thought humans could replace organs
في زمنكم، اعتقد العلماء أنه يمكن للبشر استبدال الأغضاء
and extend life for hundreds of years.
وتمديد الحياة لمئات السنين.
And they did,
وقاموا بذلك،
but eventually, they died anyway.
ولكن في نهاية المطاف، ماتوا على أي حالِ.
In your time, Earth is the only place people live.
في زمنكم، تُعتبر الأرض المكان الوحيد الذي يعيش فيه الناس.
In my time, Earth is the place people come to die.
في زمني، تُعتبر المكان الذي يقصده الناس ليموتوا فيه.
So when Navid started to show the signs,
لذلك عندما بدأت نافيد تُظهرعلامات مرضيّة،
our friends assumed I would do what everyone does,
افترض أصدقائي أنني سأقوم بما يفعله الجميع،
which is say goodbye and send her to Earth,
وهو توديعها وإرسالها إلى الأرض.
so that none of us would have to look at her
إذ لن يعتني بها أي واحد منا
or be around her or think about her and her ...
أو يكون معها أو يفكّر فيها و...
failure to keep living.
تفشل في البقاء على قيد الحياة.
More than anything,
أكثر من أي شيء آخر،
they didn't want to be around her actual physical body.
لا حبذون البقاء حول جسدها الحقيقي.
They kept referring to it as "declining,"
واستمروا بالاشارة إليها على أنها "متدنٍ"،
even though she herself was fascinated by it,
على الرغم من أنها نفسها كانت مفتونة بذلك،
the changes it was going through,
التغييرات التي كانت تمر بها،
following the rules of its nature day by day, independent of her will.
متبعة بذلك القواعد الطبيعية يوما بعد يوم، مستقلة بإراداتها.
I did send Navid to Earth.
قمت بإرسال نافيد إلى الأرض.
But I came with her.
ولكنّي قدمت معها.
I remember a friend of ours, just before we left, said,
أتذكر أن صديقا لنا، قالنا قبل مغادرتنا،
"I just think it's arrogant,
"أعتقد أن الأمر مجرد غطرسة،
like the rules don't apply to you, like you think your love is that special."
مثل القواعد لا تنطبق عليك، كأنك تعتقدين أن حبك مميز ".
But I did.
ولكنني قمت بذلك.
So, even here on Earth,
أنا الآن على الأرض بالفعل.
I kept working on how to extend life.
ظللت أعمل على طريقة إطالة عمر.
It didn't occur to me
لم يخطر ببالي
that there could be any other response.
أنه يمكن أن توجد إجابة أخرى.
I kept going back to that thing that Navid said to me
ظللت استرجع ما قلته لي نافيد
that day in Azadi Square,
ذلك اليوم في ساحة آزادي،
that without that basic constraint --
أنه دون ذلك العائق الأساسي -
a universe that granted mass to matter --
عالم قام بمنح الكتلة قيمة-
we would not exist.
لن نكون موجودين.
That's one rule.
هذه القاعدة الوحيدة.
Another rule is that all mass is subject to entropy.
قاعدة أخرى هي أن كل كتلة يخضع إلى الانتروبيا.
And there is no way to be in this universe without mass.
ولا يوجد وسيلة لتوجد بها في هذا الكون من دون كتلة.
I know. I tried everything.
أعرف. حاولت كل شيء.
I tried creating a photon box where the Higgs field was altered.
حاولت صنع مربع الفوتون حيث يتغيير مجال هيغز.
I tried recording all subatomic movements in my body
حاولت تسجيل جميع الحركات دون الذرية في جسدي
and replaying them on closed loop.
وإعادتهم في حلقة مغلقة.
Nothing worked.
لم يجدي شيء نفعا.
But my final innovation was to create a coil dimension
ولكن تمحور ابتكاري النهائي حول إنشاء بعد لفاف
with the boundaries of a body in which time moved infinitely slower,
مع حدود الجسد حيث يمر الوقت ببطء شديد،
but whose projection would appear to move in normal time.
ولكن قد تظهر احتمالات للتحرك في التوقيت العادي.
That body would then appear in our universe as a hologram --
قد يظهر إذن ذلك الجسم في الكون كصورة ثلاثية الأبعاد
here but not here.
هنا ولكن ليس هنا.
When I realized I'd done it,
عندما أدركت أنني قمت بذلك،
I ran to her room,
ركضت إلى غرفتها،
so happy to tell her I'd done it,
تغمرني السعادة لإخبارها ما فعلت،
moving through space almost normally to all eyes,
تتحرك عبر الفضاء عادة تقريبة من كل العيون،
even to my own,
حتى بالنسبة لي،
and went to lie down next to her,
وذهبت للاستلقاء بجوارها،
and forgot, and fell right through her.
ونسيت، ونمت بجانبها.
I'd found a way to eternal life,
كنت قد وجدت طريقة للحياة الأبدية،
at the expense of the one thing Navid loved most,
على حساب الشيء الوحيد الذي تحبه نافيد كثيرا،
which was to touch and be touched.
وهو أن تلمس الأشياء وتُلمس.
And she threw me out.
وقامت بطردي.
I still got to watch, though.
لازلت أشاهد ذلك، برغم ذلك.
Humans live 400 years now,
يعيش البشر الآن لمدة 400 عاما،
and we still die.
ولازلنا نموت.
And when death comes,
وعندما يحضر الموت،
the dying still pick at their bedsheets,
لا يزال المُحتضر يختار أغطية الأسرة،
and their arms break out in blue and violet blooms on the insides,
وتتحول أيديهم إلى اللون الأزرق والبنفسجي من الداخل،
and their breaths get further and further apart,
وتتقطع أنفسهم وتخفت،
like they're falling asleep.
كما لو أنهم يخلدون إلى النوم.
I've always thought that
لطالما اعتقدت أن
what gives a life meaning is adventure.
ما يعطي معنى للحياة هي مغامرة.
And death is just a problem
وأن الموت مجرّد مشكلة
we haven't discovered the solution to yet.
لم نجد لها حلا بعد.
But maybe a life has meaning only because it ends.
ولكن ربما للحياة معنى فقط لأنها تنتهي.
Maybe that's the paradox:
ربما هذا هو التناقض:
constraints don't constrain, they allow perfect freedom.
القيود لا تُحد، تسمح بحريّة كاملة ومثالية.
(Sighs)
(تنهيدات)
There was a thunderstorm here this morning.
كانت هناك عاصفة رعدية هنا هذا الصباح.
There is another forecast for tonight,
وهناك توقعات أخرى لهذه الليلة،
but for now the sky is clear.
ولكن السماء صافية إلى حد الآن.
I can't feel the wind here,
لا يمكنني الاستمتاع بالريح،
but I just asked one of the caretakers who passed by what it felt like,
ولكني سألت أحد القائمين بما شعرعند تجربته ذلك،
and she said it felt warm, like melted butter.
وقالت أنها الأمر يبدو دافئا، مثل الزبدة الذائبة.
An answer worthy of my wife.
إجابة تليق بزوجتي.
I have to find my way back to the flesh.
علي أن أجد طريقي إلى الجسد.
Until then, I take up no space but the space you give me.
حتى ذلك الحين، لا أشغل أي مساحة لكن المساحة التي تعطيها لي.